<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>NO PROMISES</title><link href="http://jdangerx.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://jdangerx.github.io/blog/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://jdangerx.github.io/blog/</id><updated>2013-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>208</title><link href="http://jdangerx.github.io/blog/208.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>John Xia</name></author><id>tag:jdangerx.github.io/blog,2013-08-15:208.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/zQqBJ3nv6Ls"
frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;208. An aquagraphic-style water curtain that displays your team name or
logo. [250 points] †&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is one of the items I worked on for &lt;a href="http://scavhunt.uchicago.edu"&gt;Scav&lt;/a&gt;
this year. I didn't complete it, but I will, someday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today is not that day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I write about the original design: the story of what went wrong and why I
can't let it go. There's a bonus section at the end about the future design, if
you're interested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, thanks to all the people (Andrew, Catrina, Cecilie, Ryan, and the
rest of Max Palevsky Scav) who helped this thing get even partway complete. This
was by no means an individual effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My original concept was a small wooden frame 18" tall and 12" wide. I mounted a
piece of PVC pipe across the top as the water reservoir. Small holes were
drilled in the bottom of the pipe to let the water out. 20
&lt;a href="http://www.sciplus.com/p/12VDC-PULL-SOLENOID_51553"&gt;solenoids&lt;/a&gt; were mounted in
a row next to the pipe; these moved in and out when I pulsed electricity through
them. Pieces of foamcore were attached to these solenoids to act as crude valves
for the water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The solenoids were connected to a rotating drum (in this case, an old Centrella
oatmeal container). I wired it up so you could use it as sort of music-box: if
you draw with conductive material (aluminum foil, conductive paint, etc.) on the
drum, the drawing would act as a bunch of little switches; as you spun the drum,
the valves would move in sync with the picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought the idea had potential. It could be a cool machine to have around -
much cooler than what the item asked for. It didn't seem too hard to make,
either. All the wiring was pretty basic stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ran into a few problems on the last day. It all boils down to one
thing. Valves are hard to make.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I tried sealing the holes from the outside by sticking a piece of
foamcore next to it. The water leaked horribly. To make matters worse, when the
valves did open, the water stuck to the foamcore flap. This made the water drip
down at weird angles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a bunch of troubleshooting, Cecilie suggested that we seal the valves from
the inside. Instead of pushing a flap up against the outside of the hole, we
would have a series of tiny plungers that went up and down over the hole. This
would solve the leaking problem and the sticking problem! The water pressure
would push down on the valve when closed, ensuring it stayed closed and not
leaky. The sticking would be conquered because there would be nothing downstream
of the hole to mess with the water. We redesigned the reservoir to have a flat
bottom so the valves would seal. We also moved the solenoids to the top so they
slid vertically. We had about 12 hours left to complete this thing. We were
gonna make it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But making accurate plungers out of foamcore is really, &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; hard, and that
is what we ended up trying to do. At 6 AM Sunday we found that they were all
misaligned. The foamcore valves wobbled around on the solenoid. The drum wasn't
big enough to accommodate the wiring. The solenoids kept falling off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;We didn't have enough time.&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I gave up, completely and utterly defeated. When I finally got myself together I
presented it to the judges. I tried to tell them how cool it would have
been. &lt;em&gt;If only they could see my vision!&lt;/em&gt; I swore I would get it working
eventually. They smiled and told me to contact them when I did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This summer I've gotten even more excited about the idea of rebuilding it.
Showing off and using &lt;a href="http://jdangerx.github.io/blog/fourthapp.html"&gt;our app&lt;/a&gt;
really hit home the visceral joy of drawing things in 3D. Drawing with falling
water would be beyond cool. I've been kicking some ideas around, to be covered
in detail after I implement them. In the hopes of forcing me to think
intelligently about them I have reproduced them below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Idea Number One:&lt;/strong&gt; 3D print the valve pieces. I should probably have done this
during Scav. Then again, spending several hours outside of HQ on Saturday night
was not an option. They will all be the same shape, and they'll be stiffer and
more accurate than the foamcore ones. They'll also attach to the solenoids
better if we design the pieces to be mounted securely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Idea Number Two:&lt;/strong&gt; While we're on the topic of mounting, I should 3D print
mounts for the solenoids, too. Then they will also be nice and solid. These two
combined should make the plunging valve action very reliable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Idea Number Three:&lt;/strong&gt; Make it taller. One thing some of the other teams
mentioned was that water falls really fast. To be able to see the picture for a
reasonable amount of time we need to either make the water fall slower or make
the screen taller. Maybe both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Idea Number Four:&lt;/strong&gt; Use a microcontroller. This could allow faster
timings. That leads to smaller droplets, which fall slower. However, we are
still limited by the speed of the solenoids. That can be alleviated by making
the solenoid travel much shorter, which might be facilitated by Ideas One and
Two. A potential drawback of this system is that we would lose the direct
connection between the drawing and the displayed water.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="scav"></category><category term="3D printing"></category></entry><entry><title>FourthApp</title><link href="http://jdangerx.github.io/blog/fourthapp.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-08-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>John Xia</name></author><id>tag:jdangerx.github.io/blog,2013-08-13:fourthapp.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm currently an intern at
&lt;a href="http://www.missionst.com/"&gt;Mission St. Manufacturing&lt;/a&gt;. We're a 3D
printing company that's trying to streamline 3D printing. If you're
not familiar with 3D printers, imagine building up an object with a
hot glue gun, carefully squeezing out layer upon layer of plastic. Now
imagine a robot doing that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the problems we are fixing is that you have to jump through a
ton of hoops to print something. Making a 3D model is hard. Once you
have a model you have to turn that into instructions for your printer,
and once you have the instructions, you have to actually print
them. We hide most of this on our server so nobody has to deal
with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can't hide the actual modeling, so we're making tablet apps that
make simple 3D modeling &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; simple.  We've got a few in the
works. Let's take a look at one that turns your finger drawings into
real things that you can hold. Its code name is FourthApp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First you draw something. It's kind of like Paint. No spray-can, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://i.imgur.com/3Ve1p3b.jpg" alt="" style="width: 400px;"/&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;img alt="" src="http://i.imgur.com/3Ve1p3b.jpg" /&gt; --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then you hit print preview. We turn it into a 3D model and send it
back down for your perusal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://i.imgur.com/ufGNaMuh.jpg" alt="" style="width: 400px;"/&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;img alt="" src="http://i.imgur.com/ufGNaMuh.jpg" /&gt; --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it turns out satisfactorily you can choose to print your part:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://i.imgur.com/xgTEGdsh.jpg" alt="" style="width: 400px;"/&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;img alt="" src="http://i.imgur.com/xgTEGdsh.jpg" /&gt; --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which ends up looking like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://i.imgur.com/vCxEIl5h.jpg" alt="" style="width: 400px;"/&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;img alt="" src="http://i.imgur.com/vCxEIl5h.jpg" /&gt; --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are, no doubt, curious as to how this all works. I'd love to tell
you, but first we need to understand the basics. Namely, what does
making a 3D model entail? Conceptually, it's pretty easy - you take a
picture, figure out what you want the model to look like, and draw
triangles on the model until it's all covered, like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://i.imgur.com/GsmBodl.jpg" alt="This is grabbed from an
open-source program called MeshLab." style="width: 400px;"/&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;img alt="This is grabbed from an open-source program called MeshLab." src="http://i.imgur.com/GsmBodl.jpg" /&gt; --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have that, you can cut it into thin horizontal slices; then
you can write instructions to tell the printer how to move on each
layer. This process is called &lt;em&gt;toolpath generation&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;slicing&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the devil is in the details. We tried several different ways
of making models, which can be lumped into one of two categories:
path-based and image-based.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started with a path-based method, which works like this: we track
the path the finger traces across the screen. Then we draw two paths
on either side, marking the bottom edges of the model. Then we play
connect-the-dots and make the triangles for the bottom face. Next we
make a copy of the bottom and move it up to make the top
face. Finally, we connect the top and bottom faces to each other to
make the sides. Ta-da!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This runs into some problems, though, when the path crosses over
itself. We end up with some triangles inside the model! The internal
triangles make it hard to determine the border of each slice. This
really messes with your toolpaths. We decided to try to detect the
self-intersections. This worked by checking each edge against each
other edge to see if they crossed. This is slow - when you start
drawing complex pictures, the brush noticeably lags behind your finger
as we accumulate more edges to check.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While trying to fix the code we started thinking about other
approaches. What if we took a screenshot and turned that into a 3D
model? We'd avoid the self-intersecting paths altogether - once you
have painted an area black, it doesn't matter if you go over it
again. It will still be black. It will be black until the end-times,
no matter how many times you draw over it. This was really exciting!
So we started hacking on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon we had something that kind of worked. The idea is pretty simple:
you look at each pixel in the picture, keeping track of how dark each
pixel is. This will correspond to height later. Each pixel has a 2D
position already. You can put that together with the heights you just
found to get a bunch of 3D points. Then you draw a bunch of triangles
in a giant game of connect-the-three-dimensional-dots, and voila! You
have a 3D model!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This method makes a lot of triangles. In fact, it makes about 10 times
as many as the last one. This means it's 10 times bigger, 10 times
harder to send over the Internet, 10 times harder to slice. To
alleviate these problems, we shrunk down the resolution of the images,
but ran into another snag: at such low resolutions, the beautiful,
organic curves (sensuous, even) that people were drawing became jagged
pixelated blocks. That can be helpful if you are trying to print out
characters from Super Mario, but that's not exactly what we want.  We
tried to find a happy medium between slow and pretty, but it wasn't
there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we've hacked together another solution. The benefit of the
path-based approach is that the model itself is much smaller and
simpler; the benefit of the image-based approach is that we don't have
to deal with self-intersecting curves. A hybrid solution gets us both
of these. The app sends us a picture of what the user has drawn. Then
we use a nice program called
&lt;a href="http://potrace.sourceforge.net/"&gt;potrace&lt;/a&gt; to trace the edges of the
drawing. From there, we connect the dots and get a model which is as
simple and smooth as a path-based one without any of the
self-intersection issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, there's still ways to improve. I'm working on an extension
to this hybrid method that will let you use different shades of grey
in your drawing to indicate different thicknesses. We can trace those
edges with potrace to get the profile of each slice. Then we can stack
them on top of each other to create the model. This lets you make
things that are bumpy on top. You'd &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; be getting somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Astute readers may notice that we don't need to turn the picture into
triangles to make toolpaths. All the printer does is fill in one
horizontal slice of the object and move up, so if we know what each
slice looks like we can make toolpaths straight from that. Luckily,
the different levels of grey represent exactly that! Instead of
stacking the slices, turning that into triangles, then slicing up the
triangles again, we can skip that middle step. This business of
translating between slices and triangles gets into deep waters very
quickly, though, and deserves its own post.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="3D printing"></category><category term="code"></category></entry></feed>