<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>no promises</title><link href="http://jdangerx.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://jdangerx.github.io/blog/feeds/real-world.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://jdangerx.github.io/blog/</id><updated>2013-08-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>208</title><link href="http://jdangerx.github.io/blog/208.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-08-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>John Xia</name></author><id>tag:jdangerx.github.io/blog,2013-08-13:208.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;!-- status: draft --&gt;

&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/zQqBJ3nv6Ls"
frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An aquagraphics-style water curtain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;208. An aquagraphic-style water curtain that displays your team name or
logo. [250 points] †&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is one of the items I worked on for &lt;a href="http://scavhunt.uchicago.edu"&gt;Scav&lt;/a&gt;
this year. I didn't complete it. At the time I felt terrible about letting down
the team. I promised myself I would complete it, someday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today is not that day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I write about the original design. What went wrong (easy to do), what went
right (also important), and most importantly, why I want to build version 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, thanks to all the people (Andrew, Catrina, Cecilie, and Ryan) who
helped this thing get even partway complete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My original concept was a small wooden frame, about 18" tall and 12"
wide. Across the top, I mounted a piece of PVC as the water reservoir. 1/8"
holes were drilled at 1/2" intervals in the bottom of the pipe to let the water
out. 20 solenoids were mounted side-by-side next to the pipe; these slid 1/4" in
and out when I pulsed electricity through them. Pieces of foamcore were attached
to these solenoids to act as crude valves for the water. As for control, all the
solenoids had a common ground. Their positive leads scrubbed against a rotating
drum. This lets you use the drum as a sort of music-box: if you put patches of
conductive material (aluminum foil, conductive paint, etc.) on it, they will act
as switches. Whenever the leads touch the conductive material, the circuit will
be closed and the solenoid will slide out, opening the valve and letting water
through. If you draw a conductive picture on the drum, as it rotates the valves
will open and close with the proper timings to translate that picture to water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sounds great (I hope)! I was really excited about it - not only would we be
able to display our own team logo, we would be able to draw anything we wanted
and turn it into water!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="scav"></category><category term="3D printing"></category></entry></feed>